<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the IX. of Nouember, 1589. By William Iames D. of Diuinitie, and deane of Christes-church in Oxford</title>
            <author>James, William, 1542-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857198</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857198</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 251:5, 790:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the IX. of Nouember, 1589. By William Iames D. of Diuinitie, and deane of Christes-church in Oxford</title>
                  <author>James, William, 1542-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Bishop and Ralph Newberie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10699 on UMI microfilm "Early English books, 1475-1640" reel 790.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 251 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 790 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLES CROSSE THE IX. OF NOVEMBER, 1589.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM IAMES D. of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Deane of Christes-church in Oxford.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Ioan. 4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ne cuiuis ſpiritui credatis, ſed probate ſpiritus an ex Deo ſint, Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam multi pſeudoprophetae exierunt in mundum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beleeue not euery ſpirit, but prooue the ſpirits whether they are of God or not: For many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iacob. 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si quis videtur religioſus eſſe inter vos, qui non frenat linguam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſed aberrare ſinit cor ſuum, huius vana est religio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any man among you ſeemeth religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiueth his owne heart, this mans religion is in vayne.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hieron. ad Pammachium.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foelices (inquit Faebius) eſſent artes, ſide ijs ſoli artifices iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Happy (ſaith Fabius) were the Arts, if they onely who are skilfull in them, might iudge of them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON by GEORGE BISHOP and RALPH NEWBERIE. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE MY ESPECIALL GOOD LORD AND MASTER Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON, lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of England, Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter, and Chancellour of the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Oxford, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſed your</hi> good Lordſhip to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Copie of my ſermon which I prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched lately at Paules croſſe: which albeit I had denied to my lord of London, &amp; diuers others before, yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it pleaſed your good lordſhip at your leaſure to vouchſafe the reading of it, I haue now at my returne hither, put it downe as
<pb facs="tcp:22887:3"/>neere as I could, and I thinke almost <hi>verbatim,</hi> as I vttred it VVherein as my chief purpoſe was to aſſwage (if it might bee) and for my ſmall meaſure I endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, the contentions ſtirred vp amongst vs: ſo haue I not kept backe my opinion, nay my conſcience, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the man that troubleth vs, and the matter by him entended. VVherein I protest (before God) that as I flattered not the Church gouernment (of I owe to no biſhop therein for any benefite receiued, any thing farther then dutie and good will:) ſo if it had bene my last ſpeach that euer I ſhould haue had, euen for the dutie I owe to Gods Church, either this, or what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God ſhould haue giuen to this ſence, ſhould haue bene ſayd. I am ſory, and it grieueth mee to ſee the heapes of Nouelties that in her Maiesties most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous raigne, and in ſo plentifull a light of the Goſpell, our inconstant Iſlanders haue brought into the world. It argueth that the enuious man ſleepeth not, but hath ſowed tares, and that they fructifie, and laboureth by all meanes, by ſea and land, to make Proſelites. There was a time when a learned miniſterie (a thing much to be deſired, as alſo your Lordſhips great care in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the liuings in your gift, and the regard which they haue, whom your Lordſhip putteth in truſt, by prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring learned men and Graduates of the Vniuerſities, doeth teſtifie to all the world, that your Lordſhip doeth
<pb facs="tcp:22887:3"/>ſeeke the like) was by the wiſeſt and most zealous thought ſufficient. But if our brethren in zeale thinke that this can not be done, but by extinguiſhing the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient names and functions of Biſhops in the Church, (a calling begunne and continued from the Apostles time vnto this day) and ouerturning the estate establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: I will ſay with the Apostle, <hi>zelum habent, ſed non ſecundùm ſcientiam.</hi> It is no way to bread a learned ministerie, either to pull downe the reward that ſhould encourage them, or the meanes to maintaine them, when they are bred. If any Biſhops haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in their callings, eſpecially in admitting of inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Ministers, (as it must be confeſſed they haue done) be it that he were an eie (though blind in this) that is, a chiefe one, or but a hand, or a foote, that is of a lower place, ſurely it is ill phyſicke for this bleard eye, or for this ſore hand or foote, to choppe off the head, or kill the body.</p>
            <p>It is hard that nothing can pleaſe theſe men, vnleſſe the Church poſſeſsions, in deede their mothers bowels be pulled out: and the cauſe why they begin with vs, is this, they muſt firſt haue a footing ſomewhere, and here they ſee the hedge is lowest. It is pitifull to ſee howe to this purpoſe in many places of this land, he is thought the onely zealous, learned, and godly preacher, that can finde moſt faults, pretend moſt wants, neuer giuing God
<pb facs="tcp:22887:4"/>once thankes for the aboundance of his bleſsings vpon this Church, and nation, which for theſe <hi>32.</hi> yeeres hath bene, yea euen at this day is a nurſe, nay rather a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all the Churches almost in all Christendome. And whereas we ought to teach repentance, amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, faith to God, obedience to ſuperiors, and charitie one to another, to rebuke pride, couetouſnes, wantonnes, newfanglednes, ſlaunderings, backbitings, and the like: if none of theſe be once named, but our ſpirituall Pastors torne and traduced, our owne vices not once touched, but the Church and Church-men paid home, then is he in many mens iudgements, a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man, a childe of God, neuer man ſpake on this wiſe. In this ſimple ſermon I did cast in my mite: if it perſwaded, I haue my hearts deſire, and God, I trust, hath the glory: if it but a litle ſtaied any, but to make a pauſe, ſome <hi>Apollos</hi> may water it, and ſome others may build vpon it. If it offended, I knowe the trueth doth not alwaies purchaſe friendes, and that <hi>nulla medicamenta tam faciunt dolorem, quàm quę ſunt ſalutaria.</hi> Surely as my meaning was not to ſowe pillowes vnder any mans elbowes, ſo was it not to grieue any, or to be contentious. For my owne part, <hi>Liberaui animam meam.</hi> This I here haue ſent, ſubmitting it, and my ſelfe wholly to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips good pleaſure, humbly beſeeching Almightie God
<pb facs="tcp:22887:4"/>to guide your Lordſhip to the glory of his name, the good of his Church, and Common wealth, and of this Vniuerſitie (not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt member thereof.) From Chriſtes-Church in Oxford the <hi>17.</hi> of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>1589.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Chaplaine humbly in the Lord to be commanded, W. IAMES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Cor. 12.</bibl>
                  <p>25 Leaſt there ſhould be any diuiſion in the body, but that the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another.</p>
                  <p>26 Therefore if one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it: if one member be had in honour, all the members reioyce with it.</p>
                  <p>27 Now yee are the body of Chriſt, and members for your part.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle S. Paul hauing plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a church at Corinth, and now labouring with the glad tidings of the Goſpel, to lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hearts of the Philippians, or (as ſome thinke) the Epheſians, who ſate in darkeneſſe and ſhadow of death: abſent from Corinth in bodie, though preſent in ſpirite; in the meane time it is not credible, what tares the enuious man ſowed in the Lordes field, among the Lordes wheate, neither how many rauening wolues entred, not ſparing the flocke. Hence there aroſe in their religion, in ſome, Apoſtaſie and falling from God, ſtarting a ſide like a broken bow: in ſome others there were itching eares, and deſire of nouelties: In their liues, ſingular iniquitie and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: in their ſacraments, intollerable corruption and prophanation: in euery thing ſtudie of partes and contention, ſo as one held of Paul, another of Apollos, another of Cephas: and, that which in this place did of all other moſt miſerablie vexe the Church, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as it were an vtter ruine, the greater, and men of more excellent gifts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned them of meaner gifts, inſulting ouer them, pleaſing themſelues aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in loue and liking with their owne excellencie: on
<pb facs="tcp:22887:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the other ſide, they on whom God had beſtowed gifts in ſmaller meaſure, enuied their ſuperiors, repined to liue vnder their ſubiection, nay, they found fault with God himſelfe, as though hee had not in due portion diſtributed his bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in this ſimilitude of the members of the body, goeth about as a good Phiſition to heale this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, ſhewing that no member, no not the leaſt, not the meaneſt, is to be contemned, nay, proouing that the meaneſt members and of leaſt accompt, are moſt to be honoured.</p>
            <p>Euery man muſt walke in his calling contentedly: <hi>Non omnes poſſumus eſſe Caeſares,</hi> ſaieth hee. They that brought not golde, nor ſiluer, nor precious ſtones to the building of the temple, yet did good offices, if they brought but wood or ſtone. If we cannot attaine to be <hi>in primis,</hi> to haue the firſt gole, yet is it praiſe woorthy if we may haue the ſecond or the third. In the building of the temple, they that laid the foundations, nay, that digged places to lay the firſt ſtone in, that hewed and ſquared the ſtone and timber, were of leſſe reputation and account, then thoſe that carued &amp; gilded the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: yet was the others worke and labour far more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie.</p>
            <p>They that till the land and ſow the ſeed, that threſh and grind the corne, are of leſſe reckoning and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then thoſe that liue in princes courts: yet is their labour and ſeruice farre more needfull.</p>
            <p>In mans body the ſoueraigntie is the heads: the eies, and eares, as in place, ſo in dignitie excell the handes and feete: yet cannot the eye ſay to the hand, <hi>I haue no need of thee, nor the head agayne to the feete, I haue no need of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22887:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea much rather thoſe members of the body which ſeeme to be more feeble, are more neceſſarie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And vpon thoſe members of the body which we thinke moſt vnhoneſt, put wee more honestie on, and our vncomely partes haue more comelines on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For our comely partes need it not, but God hath tempered the body together, and hath giuen the more honour to that part which lacked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that</hi> (as it is in my text) <hi>leaſt there ſhould be any diuiſion in the body. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is then the Apoſtles ſcope &amp; drift, that as there is great difference betwene the members of the bodie, whether we reſpect the placing of them in the body, or their force or dignitie, yet none can lacke anothers helpe and miniſterie: ſo in the church, they who are as heads or eies, that is, the chief, may not contemne the hands &amp; feete, that is, the meaneſt, but muſt giue them the more honour: and on the other ſide, they that are the handes and feete, that is, the loweſt and meaneſt, muſt not take vnto them the honour of the head, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt murmure againſt it, and that therefore, leaſt there ſhould bee any diuiſion in the body, but that as members they ought to haue the ſame care one for an other.</p>
            <p>Great was the occaſion that mooued the Apoſtle to vſe this ſimilitude, whereby he laid open their vaine &amp; fruitleſſe contention: ſo as that if they were not blind, they might ſee their owne folly, and waxe wiſe, &amp; euery man eſteeme &amp; iudge of himſelf according to his place &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereunto the lord hath called him. And I would to god we had not now a greater cauſe, &amp; might not make a more iuſt complaint then S. Paul might.</p>
            <p>As in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fire euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bringeth ſomwhat with
<pb facs="tcp:22887:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>him, either water to quench, or ſomewhat els to helpe, no man at ſuch a time ſtandeth idle; ſo I at this time, and in this place, doe bring to you this ſaying of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leaſt there ſhould be diuiſion in the body, let the members haue the ſame care one for another. If one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it, if one member be had in honor, al reioice with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In handing whereof, I purpoſe by Gods aſſiſtance, and your patience, to followe the diuiſion that Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. in his 31. homilie on this epiſtle, &amp; on theſe words maketh. <hi>Tria igitur hîc flagitauit Apostolus: Ne ſcindantur, ſed penitiſsimè copulentur: ex aequo ſibi proſpiciant: quicquid incidat, commune putent.</hi> The Apoſtle hath required (ſaith he) three things: firſt, that they be not rent or diuided among themſelues, but moſt firmely coupled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that in theſe wordes, <hi>leſt there ſhould be any diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the members ſhould haue a mutuall care one for another, and that in theſe wordes, <hi>that the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they ſhould accompt that all things that happened to one, were common to all, and that in theſe wordes: <hi>Therefore if one member ſuffer, all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſuffer with it: if one be had in honour, all reioyce with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt here is a prohibition, Let there be no faction or diuiſion among you: then, a mutual care, Let the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers haue not onely a care, but the ſame care, one for another: thirdly, not onely a care is commanded, but a commiſeration, If one member ſuffer, al the reſt ſuffer with it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, if the time will ſuffer, ſhall be added the explication and application of the Apoſtles ſimilitude in the wordes following: <hi>Ye are the bodie of Christ, and
<pb facs="tcp:22887:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>members in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſt there ſhould be any diuiſion in the body, &amp;c.</hi> Nature the common parent of vs all, who (as Philoſophie tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth) doth nothing in vaine, albeit that all her moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be by contraries; and that in this great and wide world, wherein there is wonderful and ſtrange variety, yet hath ſhe ſo tempered and mingled all things, that there is not onely not any diuiſion and diſcord, but (if we beleeue ſome Philoſophers) ſuch and ſo ſweete a harmony, that, as he ſaith of vertue, if it might be ſeene with bodily eies, it would ſtirre vp incredible loue thereof: ſo if this harmonie might be heard with our outward ſenſes, it would not only rauiſh vs more then the ſweete Syrene ſongs, but woulde repleniſh vs with an vnſpeakeable kind of pleaſure, fitter for the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gods (as they thinke) then for earthly men.</p>
               <p>In this litle world, this tabernacle of our bodies, this <hi>microcoſmos,</hi> albeit it conſiſt altogether of contrarie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, and of thoſe whereof euery one ſeeketh to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy another, and that by moſt contrarie qualities, as the extremities of heate, colde, moiſture, and drought: and albeit there be neuer any peace or reſt, vntill (as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle teacheth) there be <hi>elementum praedominans,</hi> a prędominant element that ruleth all the reſt: yet al the reſt ſo ſerue and obey it, ſo conſent all to the good of the bodie, the water aſſwaging the extremitie of the fire, the fire warming the coldnes of the water, and ſo of the reſt, euery one abating others exceedings, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſupplying others wants, that albeit (as is in the prouerbe) nothing be more contrarie then fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>heate and colde: yet as Phyſitions of diuers deadly poiſons make one wholeſome medicine, and as Bees of diuers noiſome flowers make one ſweete honie, ſo nature the beſt ſcholemiſtres, of many contraries hath made one the moſt ſweete and pleaſant mixture in the bodie. And that therefore, <hi>leſt there ſhould be any diuiſion in the bodie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this ſimilitude of the Apoſtle, albeit the head be placed as the watch-tower, the eies &amp; eares as watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the handes as champions, the ſhoulders and ſides as walles or bulwarkes, the feete as proppes to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, or as quicke poſtes to diſpatche, the tongue as an Interpretor or Ambaſſador: yet they all, head, eies, eares, hands and feete, ſo conſent and agree, euery one lending helpe to another, that that which toucheth one, is regarded and cared for of all.</p>
               <p>Barnarde in his meditations, to ſhewe howe eaſily euery man might be directed and amended by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſaith, that euery one hath in his owne houſe <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatorem, testem, iudicem,</hi> an accuſer, a witneſſe, and a iudge. <hi>Accuſat me conſcientia, te ſtis eſt memoria, ratio iudex.</hi> My conſcience is mine accuſer, my memorie the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, my reaſon the iudge.</p>
               <p>The like hath S. Baſill on theſe wordes, <hi>attende tibijp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,</hi> ſo that farther then to himſelfe, &amp; to his owne houſe, to his owne conſcience, to his owne memorie, to his owne reaſon, man needes not to ſeeke, the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cenſurer of himſelfe. In like manner the Apoſtle S. Paule, to make manifeſt to the Corinthians what a miſchiefe contention was in the Church, ſendeth them to no other place then to their owne bodies: as if he ſhould ſay, If contention and ſtrife can not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the head, eies, handes, and feete, without the
<pb facs="tcp:22887:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>danger, nay deſtruction of the whole bodie, much leſſe in the Church, vvhich is the bodie of Chriſt: <hi>Ye are the bodie of Chriſt, and members in part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that leauen which we with the Corinthians muſt purge out, before we can be ſvveete bread.</p>
               <p>Theſe are thoſe workes of darkenes, which we with them muſt caſt off, before we can put on the armour of light.</p>
               <p>This is that olde man with his deceaueable luſtes, which we muſt lay aſide, before vve can put on the nevv man Chriſt Ieſus, vvhich after God is ſhaped in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and true holines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God is charitie, and he that dwelleth in charitie dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our God is the God of peace, our Chriſt is the prince of peace, his Goſpell the Goſpell of peace, his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preachers of peace.</p>
               <p>The Prophets prophecied of him, that in his daies peace ſhould flouriſh, the Woolfe and the Lambe, the Leopard and the Kid, the Calfe and the Lyon ſhould dvvell together: that they ſhould in his daies turne their ſvvordes into plovve ſhares, their launces into ſithes or ſickles, their ſpeares into ſpades.</p>
               <p>In his natiuitie the Angels ſang peace, <hi>Glorie be to God on high, and in earth peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His vvhole life vvas an example of peace: euery vvhere <hi>pax vobis.</hi> His commiſſion to his Apoſtles, a commiſſion of peace: Into vvhat houſe ſoeuer ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teter, ſay, <hi>Peace to this houſe.</hi> In his departure hence he left peace, <hi>My peace I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e you, my peace I leaue you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gregorie Niſſen expounding theſe vvordes, <hi>Pater noſter qui es in coelis,</hi> As oft ſaith he, as vve ſay, <hi>Our father which art in heauen,</hi> ſo oft vve muſt remember of vvhat
<pb facs="tcp:22887:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtocke &amp; linage we are, namely ſonnes of the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and whither wee ought to aime and direct all our thoughts and deeds, namely to the higheſt heauens, where our father dwelleth: otherwiſe, as baſtard chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, wee ſhall beate the aire, and ſhoote at an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie. In like maner, as oft as we conſider what a God our God is, what a Chriſt our Chriſt is, what a Goſpel our Goſpell is, what Apoſtles our Apoſtles were, how that his birth, life, death, and all theſe, reſounded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as peace: ſo oft (as Chryſoſtome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) we muſt labour <hi>Vt ſimilitudinem patris indicet actus prolis,</hi> that is, that we may be fatherlike, that if wee will be coheires with Chriſt, we (as Cyprian ſaith) ſee that we abide in the peace of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For ſeeing we haue all one and the ſame father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, comforter, all one and the ſame milke of the word, and food of the Sacraments: Seeing we all inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite here one and the ſame vale of miſerie, the valley of teares, hauing all one and the ſame ſworne enemie, the olde malicious and canckred ſerpent: Seeing there is but one God, one faith, one baptiſme: Seeing we are all branches of the ſame vine, drawing all iuice &amp; moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture alike from the ſame roote, all ſeruants of the ſame maſter, children of the ſame father, and (as the Apoſtle ſaith) all members of the ſame body: why do we either contemne or contend one with another?</p>
               <p>Seeing we all runne for one gole, we all wreſtle for one garland, we all ſtriue for one crowne, a crowne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marceſſible: Seeing as this our Apoſtle ſaieth, that by one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body, whether we bee Iewes or Graecians, whether we bee bound or free, and haue bene all made to drinke of one ſpirite: Why forſake we one another? why deſpiſe we (as the
<pb facs="tcp:22887:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prophet ſaieth) the ſonne of our mother, the ſonne of our heauenly father?</p>
               <p>Chryſoſtome expounding this place of the Apoſtle in his 30. homilie on this epiſtle, ſaith that the Apoſtle vſed that word <hi>To haue drunke of the ſame ſpirite,</hi> in moſt apt and fit maner: for as we ſee (ſaieth he) in gardens, herbes and plants all, although of diuers qualities, yet to be all watred with one and the ſame raine, and all to fructifie and encreaſe: ſo we, although of diuers nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of diuers callings, yet haue all bin partakers of the ſame ſpirit, &amp; haue all taſted of the ſame grace. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one ſpirit haue faſhioned vs all, and haue made vs all one body, and fed vs with one &amp; the ſame heauenly table, haue watred vs all with one heauenly deaw from aboue, which all are to haue drunke of the ſame ſpirit: If it haue vnited vs who were before ſo farre different one from another: If the members then make one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when they all as it were do grow and knit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues together: why dreame we of any the leaſt diſſention, the leaſt difference? And a litle after, albeit the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be many and diuers, yet this is the prerogatiue of the body, to make all thoſe, although many and diuers, yet all one. In like maner, albeit the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be many, ſcattered farre and wide throughout all the world: and although (as Tertul. ſaith) that Chriſts kingdom is not conteined in any bounds, as the Germans, Britons, &amp; others are: but whither ſoeuer you go, his name is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued on, &amp; his power ſtretched out: &amp; that although ye go to the Indians, to the Moores, or whither ſoeuer els, euery where you ſhall find, <hi>In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, &amp; that word was God:</hi> yet notwithſtanding, of al theſe, although thus far diſtant, yet while they obſerue the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:22887:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of peace, as of the 5000. in the Acts of the Apoſtles, there is <hi>Cor vnum &amp; anima vna,</hi> one heart, one ſoule. This is the prerogatiue of the Church, to make that they, who are in bodies many and diuers, yet being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in ſpirit, make all one myſticall body vnder their head Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This is that catholike Church which we beleue: this is that communion of Saints, which not fleſh &amp; blood, but our father which is in heauen hath gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This is that body whereof our Apoſtle here ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, whoſe head is Chriſt, whoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers we are, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Apoſtle laboureth for agreement &amp; confort, and that therefore, <hi>Leaſt there ſhould be any diuiſion in the body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diſſention, diuiſion, is a moſt miſerable thing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye reſpect the Church, common welth, or priuate families.</p>
               <p>The contention of the Apoſtles of our Sauiour, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of thoſe things which are of the world and not of God. The diſſentions betweene Paul and Barnabas, although the Lord turned all to his greateſt glory, yet gaue the Church a ſhrewd blow, euen in her ſwadling clothes. The ſtrife betweene the Eaſt and Weſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches about the feaſt of Eaſter, armed the enemies of both againſt both. The quarels betweene Theophilus and Epiphanius, Chryſoſt. Auguſtine, Ierome &amp; Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, cauſed Chriſt and his kingdom to be ill ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Alexandrinus Strom. li. 7.</hi> ſaieth, the Heathens were wont to obiect on this maner, Ye Chriſtians diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent among your ſelues, and maintaine ſo many ſectes, which although euery one doe chalenge to it ſelfe the title of Chriſtianitie, yet euery one doeth hate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne another. For this cauſe ſaid Chryſoſtome, wee are become ridiculous both to Iewes and Gentiles,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>while the Church is rent into a thouſand pieces.</p>
               <p>The familie of Loue in reproch in their writings, call vs the deuided people.</p>
               <p>Chryſoſtome on the Actes noteth, that ſome were woont in his time to ſay, I would be a Chriſtian, but I know not to which ſide to cleaue: The one ſaieth, I ſay true: the other ſaieth, I ſay true. Which if euer it were true in any age, in this of ours is moſt true. By this wee ſee many obſtinate confirmed in their errour, many weake to be kept backe, and many wicked to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hence, to ſay in their hearts <hi>Non eſt Deus:</hi> There is no God.</p>
               <p>For albeit our contention be not ſo bitter as it was in Poperie among the Dominicans and Franciſcans, and that whole vnholy rable, euery one ſtriuing <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> one crying out, Loe here is Chriſt, another, loe here is Chriſt, which euery one hath ſeene in euery an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of euery great temple, at euery ſacring of euery maſſe, all which controuerſies Ieſuitiſme hath almoſt ſwalowed vp: yet as long as we with the Corinthians, hold one of Paul, another of Apollos, another of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, are we not carnall? doe we not make a rent in the body? I am ſory that theſe things, and greater then theſe may be ſpoken of vs.</p>
               <p>Paul, Apollos, Cephas were excellent men in the church of God, &amp; adorned with moſt excellent &amp; rare gifts: yet did the apoſtle reprehend the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for depending on them, for diuiding the church for them.</p>
               <p>If the Apoſtle might in theſe our dayes reuiue &amp; ſee our ſtrife, what itching eares we haue, how we heap vp teachers to our owne liking, how that is holy that wee will, and as long as we like, how like ſtraying ſheepe we forſake our owne ſheepfold, and like fooliſh chickens
<pb facs="tcp:22887:11"/>flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the hens wings, how in this citie ſundry aſſemblies in diuers places are thought far more holy then this daies aſſemblie, or any other at this place or the like: what may we thinke he would doe or ſay?</p>
               <p>Be it that they are (which God knoweth they are not) as Paul, Apollos, Cephas: yet as long as for them, or by them the church is rent, vntill Paul, Apollos, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas (if any ſuch be) take away the ſcandall, the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke, is there not diſſention in the body? So long as euery one draweth diſciples after him, ſeeking our owne and not Chriſtes glory: So long as in giuing honour, we go not one before another: So long as we giue not due food in due ſeaſon, but as crowes feed on carrion, ſo we fill our auditors eares with the ſuppoſed faults of other men: So long as we ſee not the beame in our own eie, but are euer hagling at the mote in our brothers eie: So long as we put our faults into the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the wallet, and lie prying into our brethrens which we hang before vs: So long as we doe nothing but with curſed Cham lay open our fathers nakednes: while we ſpeake not to the heart of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So long we make a ſchiſme, a diſſention in the body, ſo long Chriſt dwelleth not in our hearts by faith: So long we may ſeeme zelous, but not for good. So long we grieue the good ſpirit of God, wherwith we are ſealed againſt the day of redemption, and heape wrath vnto our ſelues againſt the day of wrath.</p>
               <p>As oft as I conſider a notable fruit of this contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is in deed the contempt of the miniſterie (&amp; I thinke of it oftentimes) ſo oft I cannot but tremble at the heauie iudgements which haue befallen ſo god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people. What befell Mary Moiſes ſiſter for her murmuring? Chora, Dathan and Abiram that ſet
<pb facs="tcp:22887:11"/>themſelues againſt Moiſes? the boyes that mocked olde Elizeus? what became of the holy citie Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem? Niniue, Corinth, Galatia, Epheſus, Coloſſa, Laodicea, and others, now heapes of ſtones, now dens and cages for vncleane birdes and beaſtes, now of Churches planted by the Apoſtle, become ſlaues, and bound to Mahomet and infidelitie, are things to all the world manifeſt, and need not any further explication.</p>
               <p>As oft as I heare men for their age reuerend, for their learning excellent, for their conuerſation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt reprehenſion, examples of the flocke, elders that rule well, worthie of double honor, to be reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully traduced, to be made laughing ſtocks to men and angels, and being ſuch as haue left all for Chriſt, yet to be termed Antichriſts, ſometime in the pulpit, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time at your tables, ſometime in lewde and ſhameleſſe libels, and euery where to be handled vnworthily, to be enuied at, that kings haue bene their nurſing fathers, and queenes their nurſing mothers: As oft as I behold his platforme, whome I am lothe to name, that <hi>perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus histrio</hi> Martine, who thirſteth at the ouerthrowe of Biſhoprickes, and Cathedrall Churches, like vnto him that reapeth where he ſowed not: ſo oft me thinketh that I ſee a miſerable ruine, firſt of the Vniuerſities, and ſo conſequently of the Church.</p>
               <p>It is a thing woorth the marking, that at this day in our Vniuerſities many either altogether leaue the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie, or if they ſtay, yet doe ſhunne the ſtudie of Diuinitie: ſome ſtudie Phyſicke, ſome Lawe, <hi>dat Galenus opes, dat Iuſtinianus honores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is truely ſaid by Cicero, <hi>honos alit artes, omnéſque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenduntur ad ſtudia gloria, iacéntque ea quae apud quoſque im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probantur.</hi> Honour nouriſheth artes, and all men are
<pb facs="tcp:22887:12"/>ſtirred vp to ſtudie with glorie, and thoſe things are left alone which are reproued of all men.</p>
               <p>It is a prophane ſpeech (they ſay) But <hi>no man goeth a warfare at any time at his owne charges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a goale for them that runne, and to them that ſtriue, and ſtriue lawfully, there is a crowne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</p>
               <p>After ſeede time there is a harueſt. Wee may not muſſel the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corne.</p>
               <p>The Elders that rule well are worthie of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: For <hi>if they ſowe ſpirituall things, is it a great matter if they reape temporall things?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This practiſe hath already deterred many from the miniſterie, &amp; ſome that haue entred one ſteppe, it hath cauſed to leaue their calling, and yer long be, it will cauſe that fewe will addict themſelues to the ſtudie thereof.</p>
               <p>Although I doubt not that there be in England 7. thouſand, that neuer would bowe their knee to Baal, that neuer will take their hand from the plowe, that would followe Chriſt through good report and ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that would accompt all as dung to winne him, men that knowe, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>egere &amp; abundare,</hi> to lacke and to abounde: For what ſhall I doubt what they would doe, when I ſee what they haue done, <hi>vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rani milites,</hi> olde ſouldiers, nay moſt valiant captaines: yet foraſmuch as <hi>nemo naſcitur artifex,</hi> no man is borne his craftes maſter: ſeeing that Chriſtians are made, not borne, <hi>fiunt, non naſcuntur Christiani:</hi> ſeeing men are not nowe immediatly taught of God, but (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith) they muſt <hi>attendere lectioni,</hi> attend to reading: and foraſmuch as the parents hand and heade is chiefe in the education of this childe, whoſe endeuour for the
<pb facs="tcp:22887:12"/>moſt part is to leaue them a name to poſteritie here vpon earth: what can we thinke to be the ende of this?</p>
               <p>I might vſe many examples to this purpoſe: I will onely ſhewe you this one. There is a notable ſtorie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of the mother and of the ſonnes of Zebede, the mother of an holie kinred: if any were, it is like ſhe and hers were well taught; the children the ſeede of the faithfull, ſhe asketh, they aske, ſhee asketh that her ſonnes may ſit the one on the right hand, the other on the left; The Apoſtles Iames and Iohn, the ſonnes of Thunder, elected by Chriſt to that place, taught by God, they make the ſame requeſt, as the anſwere, <hi>You know not what ye aske,</hi> manifeſtly ſheweth.</p>
               <p>Nowe if ſo good a mother, as the mother of the ſonnes of Zebede, make this ſuite for her ſonnes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy elected, already poſſeſſed of the Apoſtleſhip: if the Apoſtles, touched (no doubt) with a good meaſure of Gods ſpirite (for they had left all they had, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him) yet dreamed of an earthly kingdom: what ſhal vve thinke that <hi>animalis homo,</hi> the carnal man vvill doe?</p>
               <p>Surely in this caſe Demas vvill forſake tvventie Paules, and the yong man in the Goſpell, although he vvill bragge of doing all things commanded him, and that from his youth, yet if it come to ſuffer affliction vvith Chriſt, nay if it be but to ſell all and follovv him, vvill depart from him ſad and heauie.</p>
               <p>The parents gather for their children, not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for their parents. What parent vvill gather miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, beggerie? Who vvill lay out theſe deare pledges to reproche and ignominie?</p>
               <p>The beſt mother muſt yeelde to the mother of the ſonnes of Zebede: the beſt ſchollers that are, are inferiour to Iames and Iohn: yet both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:22887:13"/>and ſonnes, deſire the right and left hand. What may wee then thinke of our tender plantes, our yong nouices, that may be turned into what their parents will? who as in duetie they are bound, depend wholy on their parents care and prouidence.</p>
               <p>Phiſitions when they deliuer any pils, or the like me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, to prouide that they might not offend, either the taſte with bitternes, or the ſight with the vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantnes of the matter, wrappe them commonly in gold or ſugar, and ſo draw on the patient to receiue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine: euen ſo in the worke of the miniſterie, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Magiſtrates as good Phiſitions, to ſtirre men vp to that calling, whereunto <hi>vix quiſque idoneus,</hi> ſcarſe any man is fit, haue wrapped the outſides thereof in golde or ſugar, that is with recompence after long labours, whereas in deede within, if men duely wey the burthen thereof, there is nothing but that which is heauie and bitter.</p>
               <p>In poperie the chiefeſt families were drawen here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in hope to make their children Cardinals, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and great men, and with vs it was vſuall; and in Fraunce it is in euery ſecond brother, almoſt in euery great houſe, &amp; ſurely many among vs did it of a zeale, although it were but blind.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay of theſe, that vnder pretence to reforme, ſeeke to ouerthrowe all, abuſing the zeale and credulitie of the ſimple? who among them hath with Anna dedicated her one Samuel to ſerue the Lorde, or once to encounter the common enemies?</p>
               <p>To ſpeake what I thinke, and to ſpeake my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence freely, they that with <hi>Martine</hi> ſeeke the ouerthrow of all, doe offer ſacrifice to their god their owne bellie: and although they would ſeeme the moſt ſincere, yet
<pb facs="tcp:22887:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this ſeeking after the church ſpoiles, they are in deed the greateſt idolators, ſeruing their god Mammon.</p>
               <p>And theſe are they that ſtirre vp theſe tragedies, men whome nothing can ſatisfie, and yet they enuie the miniſterie, if without them or their charges, by the Lordes bleſſing they may liue.</p>
               <p>If Ananias and Saphira for keeping backe but halfe that which was their owne, were ſtroken ſtone dead; what may they looke for, that to reape where they ſowed not, ſeeke to ouerthrowe all?</p>
               <p>The deuill alſo plaieth his part in this tragedie. For as Pharao thought that there could be no more ready way to deſtroy Gods people, then by killing their male children: ſo the deuill ſeeing in the Primitiue Church, that some reſiſted vnto blood, and that ſome others moſt notable men, as Cranmer ſometime Archbiſhop of Canterburie, Ridlie Biſhop of this See, Latimer Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Worceſter, Hooper Biſhop of Gloceſter, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Biſhop of S. Dauis, Bradford, Saunders, Philpot, and others, in the middeſt of the flames to haue giuen teſtimonie to the Lorde Ieſus: and albeit he ſee and perceaue, that by our contention hee hath profited much: yet ſeeing not all things to ſucceede after his minde, he returneth <hi>ad ingenium Pharaonis,</hi> to kill the male children of the Hebrewes, euen in their ſwadling cloutes: that is, by taking away the reward of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſtudies, to drawe men by litle and litle from the ſtudie of Diuinitie, and ſo to make their deſire and zeale leſſe earneſt. For although there be nowe many (the Lord be praiſed) that can and dare meete this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in the gappe: yet he hopeth for a day, and that yer long be, when there ſhall be none to barke at the wolfe when he commeth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Principijs obſtat,</hi> he ſeeketh to hinder the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dum ſeges in herba eſt,</hi> while the corne is in the blade and greene, he maketh readie both ſieth and ſickle. He indeuoureth to ſtoppe and choke the firſt ſprings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they breake out into any ſtreames. His care is to writhe and wreſt the trees, while they be but yong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they get either toppe, roote, or great ſtrength.</p>
               <p>This myſterie of iniquitie hath not now firſt begun to worke and ſhewe it ſelfe; nay, it hath bene ſeene and noted in all ages: and to leaue off multitude of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of auncient time, I will onely bring three witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of famous memorie, <hi>omni exceptione maiores,</hi> of our age, who in the ſpirite ſawe what monſters theſe latter daies ſhould yeelde, three notable learned men, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, Brentius,</hi> and <hi>Gualter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Caluine in an Epiſtle extant to that moſt reuerend father Cranmer, Archbiſhop of Canterburie, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to haue a care, that in England there might be eſtabliſhed a certaine forme of religion, whereunto (ſaith he) as all other that beare rule there, muſt by common endeuour applie themſelues, <hi>vt praecipuae ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſint tuae partes,</hi> yet ſo, as that the chiefe care muſt lie on your ſhoulders: <hi>Vides quid locus iſte postulat, vel magis quid pro muneris quod tibi iniunxit ratione abs te ſuo iure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igat Deus.</hi> Thou ſeeſt (ſaith he) what this thy place (he meaneth of an Archbiſhoppe) requireth, nay rather, what God may exact at thy handes by reaſon of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which he hath laid vpon thee. <hi>Summa eſt in te autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, &amp;c.</hi> There is in thee the chiefe authoritie, which not onely thy place of honour, but alſo the opinion of thy wiſedome and integritie hath purchaſed with all men. <hi>Vnum tamen apertum obstaculum eſſe intelligo, quod
<pb facs="tcp:22887:14"/>praedae expoſiti ſint Eccleſiae redditus, malum ſanè intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet I vnderſtande that there is one open let or hinderance, that the Church reuenewes are laid open for a pray. A miſchiefe truly intollerable. What thinke you would he haue ſaid, if he had ſeene Martines plat-forme?</p>
               <p>Brentius in an Epiſtle to Iohn Schopper, Abbat in Heilsbrunen, prefixed before his Homilies on the acts of the Apoſtles, ſaith on this wiſe: I thinke (ſaith he) that not onely Antichriſt by his impietie, &amp; the Turke by his crueltie, threaten the deſtruction of the church, but thoſe alſo to ſeeke the vtter ſubuerſion thereof, <hi>Qui occupationibus &amp; direptionibus facultatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſticaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quas maiores noſtri ad conſeruanda ſtudia religionis contulerunt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doleſcentes à ſtudio ſacrarum literarum deterrent.</hi> Who by inuading and ſpoiling the Church poſſeſſions, which our anceſtors haue beſtowed to conſerue &amp; maintaine the ſtudies of religion, deterre and driue away yong men from the ſtudie of Diuinitie. I know (ſaith he) that the church of Chriſt is builded on a ſounder rocke, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it can bee ouerthrowen with any ſtorme, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neuer ſo vehement: &amp; that the Church which reſteth on the power of the holie Ghoſt, greatly nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the aide of externall riches: <hi>tamen quia hi qui facultates Eccleſiaſticas diripiunt, &amp; in priuatum ſuum vſum transferunt, depraedationibus ſuis id efficiunt, quo pauciores ſacris literis operam dent, &amp; ad obeunda publica Eccleſiae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera erudiantur, profectò Eccleſiam Chriſti, quantum in ipſis eſt, euertunt &amp; deuaſtant.</hi> Yet foraſmuch as they who ſpoile the Church poſſeſſions, and turne them to their priuate vſe, and by their robberie bring to paſſe that the fewer doe ſtudie Diuinitie, and be
<pb facs="tcp:22887:15"/>trained vp to doe the publike functions thereof, truely as much as lieth in them, they ouerthrow &amp; lay waſte the Church of Chriſt. And a litle after, <hi>Non ferenda bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baries eſt, vt ea organa per quae Chriſtus incrementum ſuae conſeruationis effudit, tam foedè conculcentur.</hi> It is a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme not to be ſuffred, that thoſe meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereby Chriſt had ſpread into the world the increaſe of his kingdome, ſhoulde be ſo filthily wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
               <p>Gualter on the 21. of S.Lukes Goſpell in his 183. homilie, ſpeaking vpon the occaſion of the poore wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, that caſt in two mites to the treaſurie, and our Sauiours preferring her before the richer, and thoſe that offred greater gifts: foraſmuch (ſaith he) as Chriſt is wont to behold ſuch things, we muſt remember, that he alſo ſeeth them, <hi>qui opes eccleſiaſticas ſacrilega audacia adſe recipiunt, aut ſaltem illas in vſus illicitos atque propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos conuertunt.</hi> Who with a ſacrilegious boldnes take the Church goods vnto themſelues, or els conuert them to vnlawfull and prophane vſes. <hi>Graue ergo illorum ſcelus, &amp; omni detestatione dignum ſacrilegium eſt, opes illas in vſum alienum conuertere, ſiue id publicè fiat, ſiue priuatim.</hi> Hainous therefore is their offence, and a ſacriledge worthie by all meanes to be deteſted, to conuert thoſe poſſeſſions to any other vſe, whether it be done pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely or priuately, &amp; yet it is too too vſuall &amp; frequent.</p>
               <p>And firſt he ſheweth how in the papacie theſe things are abuſed. But to let them paſſe: But among them (ſaith he) <hi>qui Euangelij nomine &amp; doctrina gloriantur, &amp; religionis reformatae ſectatores videri volunt, impudentiſsimè the ſauri illi ſacri diſtrahuntur.</hi> Who glorie in the name and doctrine of the Goſpell, and would ſeeme follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of reformed religion, thoſe holy treaſures are moſt
<pb facs="tcp:22887:15"/>impudently waſted: ſome ſnatching part to their own priuate vſe, other ſome caſting all that is left into the publique treaſurie or checker, to make thereof vayne houſes, to erect towers and bulwarkes and munitions, to make gunnes and other engines to ſhed Chriſtian blood, to pay wages to bloody ſouldiours. It commeth then (ſaieth hee) to paſſe, <hi>Vt alijs ex eccleſia diteſcentibus qui huius labes &amp; macula dici poterant, miniſtri eius fideles cum inopia &amp; fame conflictentur, ſcholae frigeant, doctiſsimi qui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dilabantur, pauperes item, &amp;c.</hi> that ſome waxing rich of the Church reuenues, who are in deed the ſpots and blemiſhes thereof, that the faithfull miniſters ſtriue with famine and penurie, ſchooles are euery where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, learned men as water ſlide away vnrewarded, and the poore to the great reproch of the Goſpell, are conſtrained from doore too doore to beg of them, who hate them and their profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Did not theſe men (thinke we) in the ſpirite foreſee the Martines and Macheuils of this our age? or is not this the ſame ſpirite that poſſeſſed the pretenſed refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in their dayes? did Caluine, Brentius or Gualter either maintaine an idole miniſterie, or ſerue Mammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or their owne belly, when thus they bewailed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued in the old Martiniſts this ſhameleſſe Church robbery?</p>
               <p>But whereunto ſhall we aſcribe this vpſtart inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? Cyprian ſaieth, that idlenes and long peace haue corrupted the diſcipline which the Apoſtles left.</p>
               <p>Euſeb. by much libertie and ouermuch indulgence, our maners bee depraued, and diſcipline corrupted, while we enuie one another, while wee derogate one from another, while we bite and accuſe one another, and ſtirre vp warre and ſtrife among our ſelues.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Vnthankfull to God, who hath vouchſafed vs ſo great bleſſings: vnthankfull to our ſoueraigne, to make a rent in her kingdome, who hath protected vs in ſo great dangers. Herein we ſhew our ſelues moſt like the Vipers brood, who neuer are brought foorth, but by renting their mothers wombe: Or to yong Mules, of whome Plinie writeth, that they being well fed, all to beate their dammes with their heeles for recompence: Or to thoſe beaſts of whom Ariſtotle writeth, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſucked vp their dammes milke, are not contented, vnleſſe they may ſucke vp their blood alſo.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer the pretence is, if this courſe may run on a while, neither ſhall God haue that glory, nor the prince that honour, nor learning that reward, nor the Church that peace, nor the common wealth that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, that in the feare of God, all good lawes, and all conſcience appertaineth to them all.</p>
               <p>Of theſe I may ſay as Seneca ſome time ſayd of the like, <hi>lib. 2. de Ira, cap. 9. Sitantum iraſci vis ſapientem, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſcelerum indignitas poſtulat, non iraſcendum illi ſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaniendumeſt.</hi> If you will haue a wiſe man to be ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry as the hainouſnes of the offence doth require, hee muſt not be angry but he muſt be mad.</p>
               <p>To haue eaten an apple as Adam did, to haue loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked backe to Sodome with Lothes wife, to haue made an Ephod as did Gedeon, to haue receiued a reward as Gehezi did, to haue denied Chriſt, to haue doubted of the reſurrection, to haue kept backe halfe a mans owne, in moſt men had bene matters not of ſo great moment: but in Adam, Loths wife, Gedeon, Gehezi, Peter, Thomas and Ananias, they were moſt hainous and grieuous offences.</p>
               <p>If Papiſts, Atheiſts, Turkes or Infidels, ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb facs="tcp:22887:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>this, it were but a matter of ſmall waight: but that they who are armed with the name of the Church doe fight againſt the Church, <hi>Eccleſiae nomine arman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; contra eccleſiam dimicant,</hi> as Cyprian ſaieth, that <hi>filij ſponſi,</hi> the children of the bridegrome, that <hi>Inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci eius, domeſtici eius,</hi> that they of his owne houſe, ſhould be his enemies, nay that hee who dippeth his hand in the diſh with vs, a man of our owne peace, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a brother ſhould doe this, ſhould ſlaunder the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſhould ſeeke the ſubuerſion of the Church, is to others incredible, in him intollerable.</p>
               <p>What is this, but (as our Sauiour ſaieth) <hi>Percutiam paſtorem &amp; diſpargentur oues?</hi> I will ſtrike the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and the ſheepe ſhal be ſcattered? nay, what if it come to this paſſe, eyther to make no ſheepeheard at all, or els to make that the ſheepeheard ſhall be <hi>paſtor idolum?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take away the reward, lay open reproch and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie, and then ſee who will put his hand to this plough. Who will then ſay with the Prophet, <hi>En ego domine, mitte me.</hi> Loe here I am Lord, ſend me.</p>
               <p>The Lacedemonians finding a boie delighted in picking out birdes eyes, put him to death: for they foreſawe that hee would prooue in time a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous citizen.</p>
               <p>The Romanes ſeeing one that in his walke did euer vſe to chop off the heads of the Poppies, adiudged that in time he would cut off mens heads.</p>
               <p>What ſhall we thinke they would doe or ſay, if they might ſee what is ſhot at by theſe men, who aime not at the heads of poppies or birds eies, but at biſhoprikes and cathedrall Churches which they planted not, the moſt renoumed monuments through Europe?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:17"/>
               <p>What will be the end, the Lord onely knoweth: but for the one vniuerſitie, I can ſpeake of knowledge, that Sathan and theſe maſter builders haue profited thus much, that where as there were in ſome Colleges and Halles where they liue at their parents charge an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or more, there are now in many not half the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in ſome ſcant twentie; in other Colledges where there is allowed maintenaunce, although the number be not much diminiſhed, yet many change their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and moſt doubt what is to be done, what courſe is to be followed.</p>
               <p>If Sathan may tranſplant theſe yong plantes, if hee may drie vp theſe fountaines and welſprings, if he may cut off this tender corne in the greene blade: what can we then looke for but Barbariſme &amp; a ſinke of all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to ouerflow all?</p>
               <p>It is truly ſaid of Ariſtotle, <hi>Finis intentione primus, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutione vltimus.</hi> The end although it bee laſt attained, yet it is firſt intended: and we here liue among men, <hi>Non cum perfectis,</hi> not with perfect men, and therefore they are to be drawen on by humane meanes.</p>
               <p>Martine Senior braggeth of an hundred thouſand, whom he termeth not a few, nor of ſmall reputation, but in maner the ſtrength of our land, the ſinew of her Maieſties royall gouernment, whom yet he reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, both Preachers and people, that they ſuffer theſe things.</p>
               <p>There are many, I am ſory to ſee it, and I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, whom this vanitie hath led aſide, many that do reuerence and admire this mans doings, vnto whom what greater euill could a man wiſh, then as he ſayd of a couetous man <hi>Vt diu viuat:</hi> ſo to them none other greater then this, that with their owne mouthes they
<pb facs="tcp:22887:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould lay open their owne reproch?</p>
               <p>The euill man out of the euill treaſure of his heart bringeth out euil things: and who ſo priuily ſlandreth his neighbour, him will I deſtroy, ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>Michael the Archangel contending with the deuil about the body of Moiſes, gaue no reuiling ſpeeches, but ſaid, The Lord reprooue thee.</p>
               <p>Neuer did any godly man write or ſpeake on this maner. None of the fathers of the primitiue Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer delt in this ſort, no not with moſt damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes. None of the moſt wicked heretikes vſed ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull taunts againſt the fathers. It cannot proceed from Gods ſpirit, to lay open Gods children to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided of Gods enemies. No man that by reading of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, praying, or meditating, talketh with God, can ſpeake with a ſpirit ſo void of God.</p>
               <p>O holy Patriarchs, Prophets and Apoſtles, holy bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Martyrs, Confeſſors, haue ye ſo wonne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to Chriſt, conuerted nations, planted faith?</p>
               <p>Is this, to reuile our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to make a ſcorne of the Lordes miniſterie, to haue all our ſpeech powdered with ſalt? Is this to miniſter grace to the hearers? Is this to edifie the Church? Is this to beare one anothers burthen?</p>
               <p>In this lauiſh and vncharitable reproching of fathers and brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I muſt ſay to them as Seneca in an epiſtle, ſaith, <hi>Similes ſunt canibus rabidis qui pluſquam exigit fames mordent:</hi> They are like vnto mad dogs that bite more then their hunger or neceſſitie requireth.</p>
               <p>It is notably ſaid of Ierome in his 3. apologie againſt Ruffinus, in a matter of farre leſſe inconuenience then this is, wherein Ruffinus delt in reſpect of Martine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly and charitably. <hi>Quid neceſſe eſt in multoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcandala
<pb facs="tcp:22887:18"/>ruinam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proferri, quae ſecretò corripere valeas aut emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re?</hi> What needeth it to haue things ſpread abroad to the offence and fault of many, which thou maieſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly either correct or amend? Of this man I will ſay, as ſometime Seneca <hi>lib. 14. epistola 95.</hi> ſaid of Marius, <hi>Quid tu Caium Marium ſemel conſulem (vnum enim conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum accepit, caeteros rapuit) &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What mooued Caius Marius who was once cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Conſull (for in the reſt they choſe not him but hee choſe them) to purſue the Teutonikes and the Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brians, and to follow Iugurth through the deſerts of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica, and to vndertake ſo many perils &amp; dangers? Was he (thinke you) mooued thereunto by any inſtinct of vertue? <hi>Marius exercitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Marium ducebat ambitio,</hi> Marius led the armie, but ambition led Marius, ſaieth he.</p>
               <p>In like maner, if you aske what hath moued Martine to this ſo great boldneſſe, whether there hath therein appeared any ſparke of vertue? I anſwere, <hi>Martinus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum, Martinum ambitio ducit,</hi> Martine leadeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ambition or perhaps auarice leadeth Martine. As that wretch burned Dianaes temple to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe famous: and as he ouerturned <hi>Omnia iura diuina &amp; humana, propter eum quem ipſe ſibi opinionis errore finxerat principatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as Cicero ſaith, to make himſelfe great, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw all the lawes of God &amp; man: ſo this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſatiffie his owne opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, careth not though he do <hi>coelum &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſcere,</hi> ouerturn all eſtates neuer ſo wel eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>It is a ſpice of ſingular enuie, nay of impietie, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie the church, that kings haue bene her nouriſhing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Queenes her nurſing mothers, that kings haue ferued the lord, that they haue kiſſed the ſonne, that is, that they haue done all things for the Church, and the aduancement of the miniſters thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is thy eye euill, becauſe I am good?</hi> Chryſoſtome in his 31. homilie on the firſt to the Corinthians, prooueth that enuie is worſe and more hatefull, then couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the roote of all euils. The couetous man (ſaieth hee) reioyceth when hee gaineth: the enuious man when another looſeth, hee counteth it to goe well with him, when it goeth ill with others, meaſuring his owne felicitie by other mens miſeries: a fruitleſſe drone pining at others profitable labors: <hi>Expreſſa quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Sathanae imago,</hi> a very liuely image of Sathan.</p>
               <p>But as Ioſeph the more he was enuied, the more the Lord proſpered him: and the more Moiſes and Aaron were maligned, the more the Lord wrought for them: and the more Iob was humbled, the more the Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted and reſtored him: ſo this fruit will come of theſe foes, that the more they ſhal ſet themſelues againſt the Church, and ſeeke to vndermine it, ſo much the more the Lord will ſtrengthen and confirme it.</p>
               <p>What grieueth it thee (ſaieth Chryſoſtome) that thy brother hath receiued a ſpirituall or temporal bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? but of whom hath he, I pray thee, receiued it? hath he it not from him from whom euery good and perfect gift deſcendeth? hath he it not from God aboue? bee angry then with him who hath giuen it, not with him that hath receiued it.</p>
               <p>Grieueth it Martine, that the Lord hath in ſo large a meaſure bleſſed his Church, that as yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſome ſteppes, ſome monuments of kingly and gracious liberalitie, that at this day our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoueraigne (whom God long preſerue) her faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Senate of elders laie not open all things to the raſheneſſe and temeritie of ſome? let him bend his anger agaynſt GOD, in whoſe handes Princes
<pb facs="tcp:22887:19"/>hearts are, a gainſt the prince, againſt the ſtate, for that they ſuffer not the Church to bee a praie vnto their teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regalius est addere quàm adimere,</hi> it is a more royall thing to adde then to take away.</p>
               <p>Sooner may one rakehell burne Dianaes temple to aſhes, then all the princes of the world build it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. In Phiſike the methode to kill, is eaſier then to cure. It is a rule in Ariſtotle, <hi>Facilius deſtruere, quàm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruere.</hi> Eaſier it is to pull downe then to ſet vp.</p>
               <p>I may well in this matter ſay as it is reported, that Ageſipolis once did: vnto whom when one reported as a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thing, that Philip king of Macedonie had in a few daies ſpace taken, and ſacked, and raſed Olinthus a moſt famous citie, and had either ſlayne or ſent into baniſhment all the citizens, and had made a miſerable ſpectacle of ſo renowmed a place: <hi>Atqui, per deos inquit,</hi> but I ſweare by the gods ſaith this heathen man, that Philip king of Macedonie, although a greatking and a mightie conqueror, yet can hee not in a farre longer time, no not in many yee res build ſuch a citie as Olin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus was.</p>
               <p>Let Martine brag of his thouſands, of his good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, in deed of his owne ſhame: yet ſhal he not in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres, nay not in many ages, erect ſuch a ſtate, build ſuch temples as this before your eyes is, endow them with ſuch poſſeſſions, prepare ſuch recompences for learning and learned men.</p>
               <p>If his plat might take place, he might then ſay, <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam inueni auream, relinquam aeream,</hi> I haue found the Church of gold, I will leaue it of braſſe: or, I found it of Marble, I will leaue it of Bricke, I found it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with Lead, I will doe as Dyoniſius did with
<pb facs="tcp:22887:19"/>Aeſculapius, in taking away his golden cloke, I will thatche it with broome, it is lighter in the ſommer, &amp; warmer in the winter.</p>
               <p>If this mans counſell might be heard, I will ſay as Cicero ſaith in another caſe, <hi>Rempublicam</hi> ſaith he, but <hi>eccleſiam</hi> ſay I, <hi>quae nunc aliqua eſt nullam haberemus,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as nowe by Gods great bleſſing, and her Maieſties gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious fauour, wee haue a Church, wee ſhoulde then haue none at all.</p>
               <p>Let no man obiect to me and my brethren, while we followe this argument, that of Demetrius the ſiluer Smith, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians:</hi> for we herein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate not with fleſh and blood. Many of vs haue one foote in the graue, and al our life ought to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of death: this wevrge, that the Church poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, Chriſtes patrimonie, is not as they deſire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo bountifully beſtowed, ſo gratiouſly protected, ſo wickedly to be pulled downe, and ſcattered abroad.</p>
               <p>If it be euill ſpent by ſome, it is their fault that abuſe it: and if ſome fewe be faultie, why ſhould all be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</p>
               <p>Euen in the beſt times, there haue bene euil Prieſts.</p>
               <p>S. Hierome on the ſixt to the Epheſians, on theſe wordes: <hi>Fathers, prouoke not your children to wrath, but bring them vp in diſcipline,</hi> willeth Biſhops and Prieſtes diligently to reade that place, who bring vp their ſonnes in ſecular learning, and cauſe them to reade wanton comedies, and to ſing filthie rimes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, ſuch as they maintaine with the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes.</p>
               <p>Eli the Prieſt was himſelfe an holie man: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he brought not vp his children in diſcipline with due correction, he fell backward, and brake his necke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:20"/>
               <p>And a litle after in the ſame place: If the Apoſtle require of the Epheſians, of Laye men, and of ſuch as were conuerſant in the affaires of the world, to bring vp their children in diſcipline, and in the feare of the Lorde: what may wee thinke he requireth at the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prieſtes hands, of whome he writeth to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie, that their children muſt be brought vp <hi>in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and all honestie?</hi> and repeating the ſame to Titus, he ſaith, A Biſhops children muſt be <hi>faithfull, not rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, not diſobedient,</hi> and (as though the childrens offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were to be imputed to their fathers,) he addeth: <hi>coniunctionem cauſalem,</hi> a coniunction cauſall: <hi>oportete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Epiſcopum, &amp;c. For it behoueth a Biſhop to be without crime, as the ſteward of God,</hi> and concludeth thus: <hi>Non est ergo ſine crimine Epiſcopus, cuius filius non fuerit ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, aut in accuſatione luxuriae.</hi> The Biſhop therefore is not without fault, whoſe ſonne is either diſobedient or diſſolute.</p>
               <p>Be it that ſome ſuch there are, that feede themſelues and not the flocke, ſome wicked, irreligious, accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting gaine godlines, that haue made the houſe of God a denne of theeues, that are but ſpots in our feaſtes: yet, the Lord be praiſed, the Lord hath his, that watch ouer Sion day and night, that weepe for her, that pray for her, that preferre Hieruſalem in all their mirth, that goe in and out before Gods people, that giue due foode in due ſeaſon, that care for the ſoules commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their charge, as men that muſt giue a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to the ſearcher of hearts and reines.</p>
               <p>This land had ſome times euil Iudges and Iuſticers, that turned iudgement into wormewood, and iuſtice into gall.</p>
               <p>There was at Rome a proude Tarquine for their
<pb facs="tcp:22887:20"/>king, yea this nation hath had tyrants: what then? Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſaith of Rome, <hi>regale ius non regni, ſedregis vitijs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptumest:</hi> the kinglie power was not taken away for the fault of the kingdome, the manner of gouernment, but for the kings faults.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian de praeſcriptione aduerſus haereticos, Quidergo ſi Epiſcopus, &amp;c.</hi> What then if a Biſhop, if a Deacon, if a widowe, if a virgine, if a Doctor, if a Martyr, fall from the faith? ſhall hereſies ſeeme to haue the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? <hi>ex perſonis probamus fidem, an ex fide perſonas?</hi> Doe we approoue the faith by the perſons, or the perſons by the faith? let them flie away, chaffe of light faith, with euery blaſt of tentation, the Lordes corne ſhal be put vp farre the cleaner into the Lordes garner. Iudas the Treaſurer became a traitor, Philetus, and Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes, Phigellus, and Hymeneus forſooke Saint Paule.</p>
               <p>S. Auguſtine ſaith well in Pſal. 131. <hi>Nonperijt frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas propter eos qui profitentur quod non ſunt:</hi> the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood periſheth not for them that profeſſe that which they are not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſostom hom. 4. de verbis Eſaiae, Vidi Dominum, Quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videris Sacerdotem indignum, ne traducas ſacerdotium, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das proditor fuit, verùm ob id non accuſatur ordo Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, nec crimen est ſacerdotij, ſedanimi.</hi> When thou ſhalt ſee an vnworthie Prieſt, accuſe not his calling: Iudas was a traitor, yet was it not the fault of the Apoſtles order, it is the fault of his minde, not of his miniſterie.</p>
               <p>As water that runneth through a woodden or a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den pipe, neither waſheth away the furrednes of the pipe, nor defileth it ſelfe, but watereth the garden whither it goeth, and maketh it fruitfull: and as the Sunne beames ſhine through many lothſome places,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>and yet neither can purge the place, nor the place pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute them; euen ſo the word of God may be fruitfull to others, when it is fruitleſſe in him that teacheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: it may be a whetſtone to giue an edge, or a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to ſtirre vp, when yet we may be as dull as ſtones, as heauie as lead: and therefore the Apoſtle praieth that when he hath taught others, he may not him ſelfe be found blame worthie.</p>
               <p>Good corne is not the woorſe for a patched ſacke, nor bad wine the better for a golden cuppe. No man refuſeth golde for the droſſe that is mixed with it, nor roſes for the thornes that growe among them. What if Saule be among the Prophets? What if Iudas be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Apoſtles?</p>
               <p>If the like meaſure might be vſed againſt any eſtates, againſt the nobilitie of this land, the iudges &amp; gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and you the Citizens of this citie, for the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded faultes of ſome fewe to ouerturne the ſtate of all, who might promiſe him ſelfe one howers ſecuritie? and we are ſome part of the bodie.</p>
               <p>But I doubt not, but as England hath heretofore had many notable men, moſt worthie martyrs, whom not England onely, but all Europe doth for many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent giftes of God admire: ſo I doubt not, but at this day there are many Abrahams, Phineeſes, Noahs, Loths, Peters, Paules, euen ſeuen thouſands, that is to ſay, innumerable, who neuer bowed knee to Baal, and would, notvvithſtanding all thoſe calumniations, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt all as droſſe to vvinne Chriſt, and let them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy Gods bleſsings in his Church.</p>
               <p>I am ſorie that I haue occaſion to carrie you thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vvith this diſcourſe: but I muſt anſvvere as Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian in another caſe ſaid: <hi>Conditio praeſentium tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb facs="tcp:22887:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>prouocat hanc admonitionem noſtram,</hi> the eſtate of theſe times prouoketh this our admonition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <p>The ſecond thing that I noted in the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s words was, that there ſhould be a mutuall care, <hi>Let the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers haue the ſame care one for another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Al the members in the bodie haue one and the ſame beginning, all one and the ſame ſubſtance, and none can doe well, if any one doe amiſſe: if one periſh or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie, it infecteth firſt the next, and ſo in time anoieth all: or if any one in a common calamitie deny helpe to another, all thereby are brought into danger: euen ſo among Chriſtians, let no man ſuppoſe, that his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns cauſe appertaineth not vnto him, but as the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the bodie, the inferior ſerue, the ſuperior rule, euery one careth for, and regardeth another: ſo in the Church, ſo in the common wealth, let the higheſt and loweſt, and all agree, and conſent to the good of all.</p>
               <p>As in the bodie, without the mutuall conſent of the members, neither all, neither any of them, can be long in health, or continue without griefe: ſo in the Church, without a mutual care, a mutual concord, nothing can ſucceede to the good of the Church, or the increaſe or aduancement of the cauſe or kingdome of Chriſt, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny member thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let the members haue the ſame care.</hi> A ſpeech of great <hi>Emphaſis,</hi> euery word carying his iuſt waight. Firſt the name of the members teacheth obedience to the head, care for all the reſt, loue to all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Let the members care. Let no man thinke his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers matters not to appertaine vnto him.</p>
               <p>Let the members not only haue a care, but the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:22887:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>care, let the members haue the ſame care, let there be no diſtraction or ſeparation of mindes.</p>
               <p>This place requireth, that they who are in the Church and common wealth, the chiefe ſhould haue good reſpect to them ouer whome they are placed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the meaneſt: and that they whom the Lord hath not exalted to ſo high place, ſhould in the Lorde obey their rulers: that as the bodie then proſpereth, when all the members agree together: ſo they all ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, when they growe vp as one man in Chriſt Ieſus, which is the head ouer all, in all, and through all.</p>
               <p>It is a great miſchiefe and preſent danger to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, if the members care not one for another: but it is farre greater, if they riſe one againſt another if they fight one with another.</p>
               <p>There is a notable hiſtorie in Eſdras, of them that builded the Temple. Wee (ſay they) will builde, and we alone will builde, and wee will builde together: as if they would ſay, Wee all couet, we all care for, wee all as one deſire the ſpeedie building of the Lordes houſe.</p>
               <p>Apocal. 12. Michael and his Angels al fight againſt the Dragon, all as one, all deſire the ſame victorie, all ſet vpon the ſame enemie. <hi>Virtus vnita fortior,</hi> force vnited is the more forcible.</p>
               <p>This teacheth vs thus much, that all muſt concurre together, that all muſt labour together, that all muſt care together. Art thou a member? care for the bodie: careſt thou not? thou bringeſt the bodie into danger, and ſheweſt thy ſelfe an euill member.</p>
               <p>All the ſouldiers of Ieſus Chriſt muſt prepare them ſelues to fight vnder the banner of Chriſt, to fight the Lordes fight, to put on the whole armour of God, that
<pb facs="tcp:22887:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may reſiſt in the euill day. For as none is crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but he that ſtriueth, and as none obteineth the goale, but he that runneth, and as no man receaueth the pennie, but he that laboureth in the vineyard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth any raigne with Chriſt, but ſuch as ſuffer with him: ſo except the members care, and haue the ſame care, they ſhewe themſelues not ſound members of that bodie, whereof Ieſus Chriſt is the heade. God hath ſo mixed all things in this worlde, that nothing, that no eſtate can ſtand by it ſelfe. <hi>Tum tua res agitur pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cùm proximus ardet.</hi> Then is thy matter in hande, when thy neighbours houſe is on fire.</p>
               <p>The husbandman ploweth not, ſoweth not for him ſelfe alone: the ſeafaring man ſaileth not for himſelfe: the ſouldier fighteth for his king and countrey, not for his owne cauſe: the marchant aduentureth for forreine commodities, but not for himſelfe alone, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo. <hi>Nemo ſibi naſcitur,</hi> no man is borne to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, no man may liue to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The king ruleth not for his owne, but for others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</p>
               <p>The preacher preacheth not for his owne, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers edifyings.</p>
               <p>It was a lawe among the Lacedemonians, as I take it, that if any thing were ſtollen from any man, his next neighbour ſhould make it good, and that becauſe he had not greater care of his neighbours ſafetie.</p>
               <p>The time ſuffereth me not to ſhewe how farre off all eſtats almoſt are, from this regard one of another.</p>
               <p>If we conſider how that many that are the heads and greateſt, eate vp the poore as bread; grinding their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: howe ſome ioyne houſe to houſe, as though they would dwell alone vpon the lande: howe they neſtle
<pb facs="tcp:22887:23"/>themſelues, as high as Eagles, &amp; (as the Prophet ſaith) call their houſes by their owne names: how you of this citie haue with vſurie eaten vp many ancient families, the fat of the lande, and by your Monopolie haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ouerthrowen all your ſiſter cities, turning the common wealth to your owne priuate commoditie: what may we ſay, thinke you? that there is a mutuall care? nay rather, neither faith nor trueth, nor loue left among men.</p>
               <p>All which duely weied, we ſhall appeare, firſt ſcant to be members, or if wee be members, ſcarce caring members: or if we care, we care not <hi>idem,</hi> we haue not the ſame care.</p>
               <p>It was notably ſaid of Ageſilaus, that citie that hath this care, although it haue no walles, yet hath it ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger walles, then walles of braſſe: and where this regard is not, although the walles be of braſſe, yet are they as weake as paper.</p>
               <p>Magiſtrates, miniſters, the higheſt, the learnedeſt in the church &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths cauſe, muſt all concurre.</p>
               <p>The cutting off of the leaſt part in the bodie, doeth not onely bring a deformitie, but a detriment to the whole bodie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. hom. 30. in 1. Cor. 12.</hi> Thoſe members of the body which are but meane, and ſeeme to haue litle vſe, yet being taken away, diſgrace the whole bodie: <hi>quid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim capillis vilius?</hi> what is more vile then the haires? yet ſhaue them either from thy eie lids, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy brovves, thou ſhalt not onely diſfigure thy face, but hinder the ſharpnes of thy ſight. Cut off the noſe, let but one foote be lame: the vvhole bodie is maimed, though it be but the vvant of one member. Cut off one finger, nay but the litle fingers naile, thou ſhalt finde the reſt leſſe able
<pb facs="tcp:22887:23"/>to doe their vvorke.</p>
               <p>There is a notable treatiſe of S. Auguſtine in his 50. homilies, homil. 15. of the maner how we ſhould loue one another. Conſider (ſaieth hee) and marke what is done among vs, euen naturally how euery member ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth one for another. <hi>Ecce, ſpinam calcat pes,</hi> Behold, the foot ſtriketh againſt a thorne. What is ſo farre off from the eie as the foote? farre diſtant in place, yet neere in affection: the thorne pricketh but in one and that a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle place, and yet ſee the backe bone boweth it ſelfe, the eyes ſearch, the eares hearken, if any can giue help: the hands handle moſt tenderly, and although the eies, the eares, the heart, the head, the hands, and all be wel, yea the foote it ſelfe, euery where ſauing where it is pricked: yet heart, eyes, eares, hands and all, although they be not hurt, yet haue a mutuall care to cure and comfort the part grieued, though it be but the litle toe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mutuis auxilijs ſtant omnia,</hi> All things are maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by mutuall helpes.</p>
               <p>Gen. 13. When Abraham heard that his nephew Loth was taken and caried away of the fiue kings that made warre againſt Sodome, he prepared himſelf with 318. borne and bred vp in his houſe, and purſueth the enemies, ſlaieth the kings, and recouereth and resku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Loth and all his ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>In the 10. of Ioſue when Adonizedek king of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Hoham king of Hebron, Piraking of Iarmuth, Iaphia king of Lachis, Dabir king of Eglon, make war againſt the Gibeonites, for that they had ioined them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to Ioſue, who had deuoted himſelfe vnto the Lord: then ought Ioſue as a feeling member, to ſend ſuccour to them of Gibeon, to purſue the enemies: the Lord will ſhut them vp in a caue, Ioſues ſouldiers ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:22887:24"/>ſet their feete vpon their necks, Ioſue ſha and hang them vp vpon ſiue trees, vntill the Euening. Abraham, Ioſue, al that feare God, muſt ſet themſelues agaynſt idolaters, Gods enemies.</p>
               <p>In like maner, if we bee liuely members vnder our head Chriſt Ieſus, let vs not onely haue a care, but the ſame care with them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is moſt honorably done of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, while the Pope and Spaniard, and all the Leaguers bend themſelues againſt our neighbour king, becauſe he hath ſet himſelfe to ſeeke the Lord, and to aduaunce his trueth, to aſſiſt that Ioſue: and we as members are to pray, that the Lord may abate the edge of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſword, and graunt him victorie in the daie of battell.</p>
               <p>In the firſt of Iudges, Iudah ſayd vnto Simeon his brother, Goe vp with mee into my lot, that wee may fight againſt the Chananites, and I will goe vp with thee into thy lot alſo: as if hee ſhould confeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being ſeuered, to bee vnable to match the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanites, but if either would take care of other, eyther helpe other in his lot, that then there were hope of happy victorie. O that thoſe things might take deepe roote in our hearts, that Iudah would helpe Simeon in his lot, and Simeon helpe Iudah in his lot: if Chriſtian princes abroad, and wee as brethren at home, would helpe one another, wee ſhould with eaſe ere this haue ſubdued all the Chananites.</p>
               <p>If ye of the laitie would fauour the miniſterie; If we of the miniſterie would painfully preach to, and pray for you of the laitie; If we would helpe you in your lot, and you helpe vs in our lot: ſurely Gods glory would be much more promoted, and our comfort on both
<pb facs="tcp:22887:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſides farre the greater: where this care taketh place, all things proſper.</p>
               <p>It is truly ſaid of him, <hi>Concordia res paruae creſcunt, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia maximae dilabuntur,</hi> by concord ſmall things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, by diſcord the greateſt are ſoone waſted.</p>
               <p>Seneca reporteth in an epiſtle of his, that M. Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa a famous man was woont to ſay that hee did owe much to this ſentence: <hi>Hac ſe aiebat &amp; fratrem &amp; ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum optimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> factum,</hi> for that hereby he ſaid he was made the beſt brother, and the beſt friend.</p>
               <p>If an heathen learned thus much by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and humane philoſophie, what ought wee to ſay, who haue bene taught as the trueth is, and haue taſted how ſweete the Lord Ieſus is?</p>
               <p>This may teach vs (as the Apoſtle ſaith) one to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and helpe another, one to edifie and build vp ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it be poſſible, and as much as lieth in vs, to haue peace with all men, one to beare anothers burdens, that ſo we may fulfill the law of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>S. Auguſtine in his booke of 83. queſtions, and in the 71. queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, expounding theſe words, <hi>Beare one anothers burden,</hi> citeth out of Plinie a ſtorie of the Hartes, which when they paſſe ouer the ſea to any Iſland to paſture, doe on this ſort order themſelues, that they beare the burthen of their heads, by reaſon of the weight of their hornes, one vpon anothers backe, ſo as euery one that commeth behinde, doeth thruſt out his necke and laie his head on him that goeth before: and becauſe hee that leadeth the reſt, hath none vpon whom hee may reſt his head, <hi>Vicibus id agere dicuntur, &amp;c.</hi> they are ſaid to do it by courſes: ſo as that he being wearied with the weight of his hornes, doeth caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and commeth after all, &amp; into his place the next
<pb facs="tcp:22887:25"/>ſucceedeth, whoſe head he did beare when hee led: ſo one bearing anothers burthen they paſſe the ſea, vntill they come to firme land.</p>
               <p>If nature haue thus taught wild beaſts, what ought, not naturall men or philoſophers, but Chriſtians who haue after another ſort learned Chriſt, to doe?</p>
               <p>If Harts doe ſo agree, and ſo one ſupport and beare anothers burthen, and that in the middeſt of the ſea, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the raging waues: if there one forſake not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but all alike, the greateſt as well as the leaſt, yeeld to thoſe mutuall ſeruices, and that onely for a litle pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſake: what ought we to doe, who floting in this ſea of miſeries, yet looke for a citie hauing a foundation, for better foode, the ioyes prepared for the iuſt in the land of the liuing?</p>
               <p>Thus it ſucceedeth euery where not onely among Chriſtians and naturall men, but euen among the beaſts of the field, while there is a common care one for another.</p>
               <p>I might here take iuſt occaſion to ſpeake againſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill diſſention, where none careth for other, but euery one ſeeketh to deſtroy and ſupplant another.</p>
               <p>While the two eyes of Greece, Athens and Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, were either agaynſt other, neither caring for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they both felt the ſmart, and Greece became a praie to the enemie. While Hanno and Hanibal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied either other, neither caring for the good eſtate of Carthage, Carthage came to her confuſion.</p>
               <p>While the two brethren Etheocles and Polinices, contended about the kingdome of Thebes, neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the one the other, nor the good ſtate of the kingdome, they both loſt themſelues, and that they fought for.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>While Ariſtobulus and Hircanus contended for the kingdome of Hierusalem, forgetting that they were brethten, or that it was the holy citie, or that there was the holy temple, the temple of the Lord, Hieruſalem is made a praie to the Romans power.</p>
               <p>Ioſephus reporteth, that not the famine within, which was ſuch that Marie the daughter of Eleazar did eate her owne child, nor the ſword without, did ſo much harme to them, and good to the enemies, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the brethren &amp; the mutinie of the multitude.</p>
               <p>It is notablie ſayd of Plutarch, <hi>In praeceptis politicis, Nullum in medio reliquit fortuna certaminis praemium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is an excellent ſtorie in Liuie, <hi>lib. 1. decad. 1.</hi> to this purpoſe woorth the marking. There was between the Romans and the Albans deadly fued, ſuch as no way might bee ended but by dint of ſword: on both ſides great preparation, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both armies had now as it were pitched the field, and ſet their battell in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and were now not farre diſtant the one from the other, euen readie to ioyne battell, and to encounter together, whereof was ſure to follow much bloodſhed that might threaten the ruine of both kingdoms: Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Suffetius generall of the Albanes, goeth to king Tullus, to whom he ſpeaketh on this wiſe: Let Tullus king of Romans vnderſtand thus much, that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trurians, a people mightie by ſea and land, enuie vs both, and onely looke while wee ſpoyle one another, <hi>Vt nobis bello exhauſtis, &amp; Roma, &amp; Alba potiantur:</hi> that when we ſhall haue diſpatched one another, they may make a praie of Rome and Alba. Let vs therefore thinke of ſome other way, that ſo great a ſlaughter may not happen to both nations, Tullus receiueth the condicion: and by chance there were in either ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb facs="tcp:22887:26"/>three brethren, three of Rome, three of Alba, three Horatians, three Curiatians, neither vnlike in age or abilitie. The condition is, that theſe three of either ſide ſhould end the matter, <hi>Et ibi imperium fore, vnde victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria fuerit,</hi> that there the ſoueraigntie &amp; empire ſhould be, where the victorie was. The kings on both ſides encourage their champions, ſhewing that in their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and proweſſe depend the eſtate of their gods, their kings, their countries, and their parents, that on them were caſt the eies of the whole armie. The trumpets ſound, the champions on both ſides with might and maine grapple together, although not with the ſtrength, yet with the courage of both armies: none of them nowe regarded his owne eſtate, for that on them depended the good eſtate of Rome, of Alba, the religion of their Gods, the ſoueraigntie of their king, the ſafetie of themſelues and countrey. The glittering of their armour, the claſhing of their ſwordes, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling droppes of blood kept the Romans and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans <hi>Spem inter metúmque,</hi> betweene hope and feare. At the length two of the Romanes fell downe dead, and the three <hi>Curiatij</hi> were ſore wounded, the third Roman being not once touched: who ſeeing himſelfe vnable to encounter three, <hi>Fuga ſibi conſulendum puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit,</hi> determined to take himſelfe to his heeles: which they beholding, follow him as faſt as euer they can, and as their woundes would giue them leaue: and while euery one did as it were burne with deſire of glorie, forgetting their owne feebleneſſe, their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns woundes and weakeneſſe, they did not as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body hold together, but as they were of the more ſtrength, did runne the faſter, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke their brethren: which when the Roman once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:26"/>ſeeing them a good way aſunder, he ſuddenly turned backe, and killed him that was next, wounded before and wearied, before the ſecond could ſuccour him, and the ſecond alſo, before the third could reſcue him: there now remained onely one-to one, and of the Albans he that came lag, moſt wounded, moſt weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, euen cleane ſpent. Here was great inequalitie, great oddes. The Roman vntouched, imbrued in blood, puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with victorie, Behold (ſaieth hee) here lie thy brethren dead, and ſo thruſt him through that was ſcant able to hold his ſhield.</p>
               <p>True it is, that we of Alba haue had a long contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Romans: we haue perhaps of three ſlayne two, that is the greater part, yet ſo, as we are all woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and although we bee all yet left aliue, and haue but one Roman to encounter withall, yet if in purſuit of him, wee hold not altogether, but runne ſtragling, euery man as the heate of his affections carie him, as did theſe <hi>Curiatij,</hi> if he may once deuide vs, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs, although three to one, yet if the mans polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, may ſeparate vs, it is not credible how eaſilie hee will ouercome vs. Thus are thoſe three euery one not caring for anothers ſafetie, as no good members of Alba, cauſers of their owne ſlaughter, and of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſubiection of their countrey to the Romans. Shall I apply this to our ſelues, how we in the chaſe of this Roman are diuided? Or ſhall I ſhew how we haue now for many yeeres left folowing after him, &amp; being all wounded by him, haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fighting, nay to wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nay to killing one of another, ſhething our ſwords in our brothers bowels? O my brethren, that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers would haue the ſame care! O that we would ſeeke thoſe things which belong to the peace of Hieruſalem!</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:27"/>
               <p>It is a fable, but hath a morall, that the Mouſe and the Frogge did ſo long contend for the maſterie of the marriſh ground, vntill the Kite in their contention caught vp both. The Lion and the Beare fell at one time on a yong Colt: either claimeth the praie to bee his: the lion alledgeth his ſoueraigntie ouer the beaſts: the Beare pleadeth his ſtrength, neither is content to deuide with other: they both fight ſo long, vntil being wounded and wearied, they are enforced to lie downe to take breath: then the Foxe, who all the while lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind a buſh to behold their fight, to both their griefes tooke the whole praie from both.</p>
               <p>Ariſtotle in his 9. booke <hi>De hiſtoria animalium,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the Cibind and the Eagle, that they doe ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently contend and ſtriue, that oftentimes claſping together in the aire, they fall downe vnto the earth, and are taken vp aliue of ſheepeheards: and that the Cranes in like maner fight ſo eagerly, that they will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abide to bee taken vp of men paſſing by, then to leaue off.</p>
               <p>It was a heauie iudgement of the Lord agaynſt the Madianites, who came in number as many as the graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers are, or as the ſand in the ſea ſhore againſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon: and againſt the Philiſtines, who in like maner came againſt Saul: and againſt the Ammonites and Moabites, and the inhabitaunts of mount Seir, who came againſt Iehoſephat, that euery of them forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their enemie againſt whom they waged battell, ſhould euery one ſlay another.</p>
               <p>Let vs (beloued in our Sauiour) conſider with our ſelues, that moſt mightie nations, moſt valiant people, moſt flouriſhing Cities, Greece, Carthage, Thebes, and Hieruſalem, for want of this due care, by this one
<pb facs="tcp:22887:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>miſchiefe of diſſenting among themſelues, to haue come to an vtter ouerthrow: on the other ſide, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham with 318. agreeing together, to haue deliuered his nephew Loth, and to haue killed the fiue kings: and Ioſue, with an handfull in reſpect, to haue ouercome fiue mightie princes, with all their power.</p>
               <p>It is well ſaid of Seneca, <hi>Auxilia humilia firma con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſus facit.</hi> Small helpes by conſent growe mightie.</p>
               <p>If wee haue the courage of Lyons, the ſtrength of Beares, yet if we contend about our pray, the Foxe will deceaue both.</p>
               <p>If wee haue the eies and winges of Eagles, or the ſtrength of the Cibind or Cranes, that we dare fight in the aire, yet ſhall wee be taken vp by ſheep heards, by them that paſſe by. What? are we either more, or migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier then the Madianites, Ammonites, Philiſtims, or Moabites?</p>
               <p>It was a great plague that the Lord laid vpon them, that euery one of them ſhould be anothers ſlaughter man.</p>
               <p>Be it that there be two Romanes already by vs van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, it may be that there is yet one left vntouched: if he can ſeparate vs, ſurely he will deſtroy vs, for wee are already wounded: but what if wee who are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wound one another?</p>
               <p>Neſtor perſwading Achilles and Agamemnon to concord, vſed this reaſon, For that otherwiſe Priamus and his ſonnes would laugh at their variance. In like manner, Priamus of Rome, and his ſonnes, our ſworne enemies, ſeeing our hoſtilitie in bookes, in reprochfull taunts, and ſlaunderous libets, laugh at it, and cry ouer vs, There, there, loe ſo would we haue it.</p>
               <p>It was wiſely ſaid of Socrates, as Xenophon repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>that without mutuall care and concord, neither could any citie be well gouerned, nor any houſe quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inhabited.</p>
               <p>Sixe things there be which my ſoule hateth, ſaith the Lord, and the ſeuenth my ſoule deteſteth: namely, him that ſoweth diſcord among brethren.</p>
               <p>He doth iniurie to Chriſt, that ſetteth Chriſtians at contention. Wherefore if this, namely the members not to care for the members, not to haue the ſame care, hath brought confuſion to moſt mightie nations. If it make vs a laughing ſtocke to our enemies: if it ſhewe vs not to be the ſonnes of God: if he be not onely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but accurſed, that ſetteth debate betweene bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: If euery kingdome or houſe deuided within it ſelfe, ſhall come to deſtruction: If when we bite one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, we ſhall be conſumed one of another: let vs haue brotherly loue among vs, brotherly care one for another.</p>
               <p>Salomon ſaith, that a brother that is holpen of his brother, is as a ſtrong or well fenced citie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ecce quàm bonum, &amp; quàm iucundum eſt, habitare fratres in vnum.</hi> Firſt <hi>Ecce,</hi> beholde, with an admiration, and then, howe good, and howe pleaſant a thing it is, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwel together in vnitie! not contented as you ſee, to ſay, It is good, or it is pleaſant, but beholde, how good and howe pleaſant it is. Many thinges are good that are not pleaſant, as affliction, and the like: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things pleaſant that are not good, as the bread of wickednes: but brethren to dwell together in vnitie, is, Beholde how good and how pleaſant, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>S. Auſten on this Pſalme ſaith: <hi>Ita dulcis est ſonus, vt qui pſalterium neſciunt, ipſum tamen verſum cantent.</hi> The ſound (ſaith he) of <hi>Ecce quàm bonum, &amp; quàm iucundum
<pb facs="tcp:22887:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſt, habitare fratres in vnum,</hi> is ſo ſweete, that they who knowe not the pſalter, yet ſing the verſe.</p>
               <p>The ſumme and concluſion of this point is, that we loue one another: <hi>Thereby ſhall all men knowe</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour,) <hi>that you are my diſciples, if ye loue one another, as I haue loued you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owe nothing to any man, but this, that ye loue one another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For in Chriſt Ieſu, neither circumciſion auaileth any thing, neither vncircumciſion, but faith that worketh by loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ende and fulfilling of the lawe is loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs therefore not loue in worde or tongue, but in deede and trueth:</hi> with a loue without diſſimulation, with ſuch a loue, swill couer the multitude of offences.</p>
               <p>It was the Apoſtles ioye, which he by many obte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations beſought them to fulfil, to be like minded, and as here is required the ſame care, ſo there the ſelfe ſame loue. Phil. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs therefore</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues) <hi>conſider one another, to prouoke to loue, and to good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might ſpeake, and ſo had purpoſed, much more to this ſence: but the time hath ſo ouertaken me, that I muſt referre that, as alſo the third part of mutuall compaſsion, and the application: <hi>Yee are the bodie of Christ, and members for your part,</hi> to your Chriſtian conſideration. Onely this I wiſh you all conſider, that as in the griefe of the bodie, the very heart ſigheth, the cies ſhead teares, the head aketh, the ſtomacke refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth foode, the whole bodie is made feeble, though it be but the griefe of a finger, or of a toe: ſo in the church there ought to be a ſympathie, and fellowe feeling, to weepe with them that weepe, to reioyce with them that reioyce.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22887:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Who is weake (ſaith the Apoſtle) and I am not weake? to remember them that are bound, as bounde with them.</p>
               <p>It is moſt aptly ſaide of Chryſoſtome to this ſence, <hi>hom. 35. in Matth.</hi> Doeth thy brother ſuffer trouble or loſſe? if thou be ſorie for him, thou art placed as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the bodie of the Church: if thou ſorow not, if thou ſuffer not, thou art cut off, and peraduenture thou therefore ſoroweſt not, becauſe thou art cut off. <hi>Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu dolet membrum, quamdiu in corpore continetur: ſi autem abſciſſum fuerit, nec dolere poterit, nec ſentire.</hi> The member ſo long grieueth, as it is conteined in the body: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut off, it hath neither ſorowe nor ſence: and ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian that contemneth his brother, <hi>Quia iam eſt alienus à corpore, ideò affectum charitatis non tenet in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</hi> Becauſe he is nowe a ſtranger from the Church, therefore he holdeth not the affection of charitie in his heart.</p>
               <p>This your Sympathie and commiſeration ſhould ſhewe it ſelfe in releeuing your needie brethren. in hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ſuccouring the poore maimed ſouldiers, in aiding and aſſiſting your afflicted brethren in Fraunce and Flaunders for the Goſpels ſake.</p>
               <p>Nowe is the time when Pharaoh of Rome, Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib of Spaine, Rabſace of Flaunders, in their pride ſet themſelues againſt the Lorde, and his Chriſt, ſeeke to diſplace your dread Soueraigne, (whome let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God euer mightily to maintaine) to conquere &amp; ſubdue this nation to a forraine yoke, to ſpoile man, woman, and childe, and to make vs all ſlaues to their Romiſh and Spaniſh crueltie.</p>
               <p>A heathen man could ſay, <hi>Qui non propulſat cùm poteſt iniuriam, &amp;c.</hi> He that doth not put away force or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb facs="tcp:22887:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>when he may, is as much in fault, as if he ſhould forſake his parents or his countrey.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Quod vni existis, &amp;c.</hi> What you haue done to one of theſe for my name ſake, you haue done it vnto me: is it true in reliefe of the bodie with foode and raiment, and not in preſeruing the body and ſoule from idolatrie and ſuperſtition?</p>
               <p>In the 9. of the Actes, Chriſt ſaith to Saule, Saule, Saule, why perſecuteſt thou me? Saule perſecuted the Chriſtians, not Chriſt that was in heauen, yet (ſaith Chriſt) becauſe he had a compaſſion with his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, his Church, that that might be verified which the Apoſtle here ſaith: <hi>If one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it. Quando minimos meos perſequeris, me perſequeris.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou perſecuteſt the leaſt of mine, for my name ſake, thou perſecuteſt me.</p>
               <p>It is ſaide by our Sauiour, what you haue giuen to one of theſe, ye haue giuen it to me: for he that giueth to the poore, lendeth to the Lorde: and truely in this caſe, he that aſſiſteth them that fight the Lordes fight, lendeth vnto the Lord, &amp; it ſhall be paied him againe, and the Lorde ſhall deliuer him in the day of trouble.</p>
               <p>In which reſpects, in theſe daies of the Spaniſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended inuaſions, of the ſeeking to ſupplant Chriſt and his members in our neighbours of Fraunce, ye ſhould not only not murmure at any helpe ſent them, or looke to be preſſed thereunto by power or authoritie, but freely and chearefully to offer, to make a free will offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſerue the Lord.</p>
               <p>The cauſe is Chriſtes, the enemie ours as well as theirs, and therefore we, aſwell as they, ſhould ſuffer with them.</p>
               <p>The king is the Lordes annointed: he is our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb facs="tcp:22887:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>a good neighbour, &amp; ſuch a one as feareth God, that hath from his youth borne the Lordes yoke: the danger great, for that through his ſides he ſhooteth at vs, and by his ouerthrow, making as it were a bridge on his backe, the enemie hopeth for an entrance to vs.</p>
               <p>Let vs all therefore in this caſe, for aſmuch as the danger is common, make the care common: let vs not ſeeke to lay all on her Maieſties backe, whoſe care, and coſt is onely for vs and our ſafetie, who for Chriſt and his Goſpell ſake, for the freedome and libertie of her loyall and louing ſubiects, to ſerue the Lorde her God, hath aduentured the wrath and indignation of moſt mightie and malicious enemies, and hath ſuffered the moſt deteſtable and damnable practiſes of moſt vile and wicked wretches. But the Lorde her God, whome ſhe ſerueth, hath ſtoode by her, and deliuered her, and they are fallen into the pitte they prepared for others, and haue inherited the reward of blood.</p>
               <p>There was a time, when our ſwordes were turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plowe ſhares: but the caſe is nowe altered, we muſt turne our ſhares into ſwordes, and he that hath no ſworde, muſt ſell his coate and buy aſworde.</p>
               <p>Surely as Gods cauſe againſt whome they fight, is the principall motiue that ſtirreth vp thoſe our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thus to maligne vs: ſo a ſecond adiuuant cauſe is, that abundance and plentie, vvherevvith the Lord our God in his mercie, hath ſo richly bleſſed vs. Novve as our Sauiour ſaith, he that vvill ſaue his life ſhall loſe it: ſo vvhen Gods cauſe and our Countries requireth it, he that vvill ſpare then, ſhall loſe all.</p>
               <p>I may ſay of this kind of men that hoord vp their filuer and gold, that are rich in plate and iewels, and the like, (which theſe men thirſt after) as Aiax once did to
<pb facs="tcp:22887:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vliſſes, when they ſtroue for Achilles armour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cur ſpolieris erit, non cur metuaris ab hoſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So this abundance, nay rather this cloſe keeping of it, when our prince and country may require it, where it ruſteth and profiteth not, <hi>Cur ſpolieris erit.</hi> It ſhall be a cauſe why wee ſhall be ſpoiled, not why wee ſhall be feared.</p>
               <p>But I ſee I forget my ſelfe and abuſe your patience: I muſt therefore, the time being ſpent, without repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion end, humbly beſeeching the almightie God for his great mercy ſake, ſo to ſofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our hard hearts, that there be no ſtrife or contention among vs, but that all bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may be laid aſide, and that, as members, we may all haue a care, and the ſame care, that if one ſuffer, all may ſuffer with it, if one be honoured, all may reioyce with it, that as we are the body of Chriſt and members for our part, ſo we may with one mind and one mouth, glorifie God the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the holy ghoſt, three perſons in one moſt glorious Trinitie, one God in Vnitie, might and maieſtie, be yeelded all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, prayſe and glory, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
